Guide to the James Luther Kibler papers, 1857-1957 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
James Luther Kibler papers 1857-1957 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Kibler, J. Luther (James Luther), 1867-1953
12.0 linear feet Extent: Approx. 7200 Items
James Luther Kibler (1867-1950) was a public school teacher, prominent Lutheran layman, and active member of the Socialist Party of Virginia. Collection comprises correspondence, printed material, writings, clippings, and photographs, pertaining to Kibler's interest in the history of Virginia, Lutheran issues, his work with the Socialist Party of Virginia, his newspaper column Kibler's Kolumn, and other topics. Also included are over forty scrapbooks compiled by Kibler dating from 1913 to 1953, in which are mounted clippings (including his column), letters, notations, royalty receipts, postcards, and photographs.
kiblerjames
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The James Luther Kibler papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 1974.
Biographical Note
For twenty years, James Luther Kibler was a public school teacher, and in 1898 was the prime mover in the organization of the Virginia Teachers Co-operative League, the progenitor of the Virginia Education Association. In 1899 he married Henrietta Shipe of Fort Valley, Virginia. Their children were James Otto and Orpha Evangeline. Kibler was a prominent Lutheran layman and a Democrat until he broke with the party in 1932 and joined the Socialist Party. In 1933 he ran on that party's ticket for the Lieutenant-governorship of Virginia, but was defeated. From 1934 to 1936 he was Secretary-Treasurer of the Socialist Party of Virginia. He was drafted by the party to run for the U.S. Senate in 1936 but was compelled to withdraw from the race.
After his school teaching days, he was active chiefly as a journalist and historian. From 1930 to 1935, he wrote Kibler's Kolumn for the Virginia Gazette. He was also the author of several volumes and numerous articles, other than his Kolumn. For some years he was active in the Federal Writer's Project. He also was connected with Subsequent History and more than one guide service that conducted tours of Williamsburg, Jamestown, and Yorktown.
Collection Overview
Collection comprises correspondence, printed material, writings, clippings, and photographs, all pertaining to Kibler's interest in the history of Virginia, Lutheran issues, his work with the Socialist Party of Virginia, his newspaper column Kibler's Kolumn, and other topics. Also included are over forty scrapbooks compiled by Kibler dating from 1913 to 1953, in which are mounted clippings (including his column), letters, notations, royalty receipts, postcards, and photographs.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Kibler, J. Luther (James Luther), 1867-1953; Socialist Party (U.S.); Virginia Education Association; Virginia Gazette; Lutherans -- Virginia; Virginia -- History; Photographs; Photograph albums; Scrapbooks
Contents of Collection
- James Luther Kibler Papers, 1857-1957 and undated, (8 boxes; 1 oversize folder)
  - Correspondence, 1859-1957 and undated (Box 1)
  - Writings, 1857-1957 and undated (Box 2)
  - Writings, undated (Box 3)
  - Printed materials, 1892-1953 and undated (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 1866-1948 and undated (Box 4)
  - Legal papers, 1907 and undated (Box 4)
  - Genealogy, 1951-1953 (Box 4)
  - Financial papers, 1863-1940 (Box 4)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 4)
  - Clippings, 1873-1953 and undated, (14 folders) (Box 4)
  - Scrapbooks and composition book, 1913-1932, (3 items) (Box 4)
  - Scrapbooks, 1925-1952, (9 items) (Box 5)
  - Scrapbooks, Socialist Party of Virginia ledger, and composition book, 1895-1953, (17 items) (Box 6)
  - Scrapbooks and photo album, 1918-1951, (16 scrapbooks, 1 album) (Box 7)
  - Scrapbooks, 1925-1952, (3 items) (Box 8)
  - Oversize materials (Opaperfolder 1)